<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Home on Liam Ellul&#39;s Blog</title>
    <link>https://liamellul.github.io/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Home on Liam Ellul&#39;s Blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 03 Oct 2023 19:53:12 +0200</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://liamellul.github.io/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Ethereum&#39;s Consensus &amp; Staking Solutions</title>
      <link>https://liamellul.github.io/posts/eth-staking/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Oct 2023 19:53:12 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://liamellul.github.io/posts/eth-staking/</guid>
      <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Consensus mechanisms are a set of rules that allow decentralized networks to agree on a single version of the truth without a central authority figure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;why-ethereums-consensus-mechanism-changed&#34;&gt;Why Ethereum&amp;rsquo;s consensus mechanism changed&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last year in response to environmental concerns of how much energy and associated CO2 emissions the Ethereum’s consensus mechanism was using, Ethereum upgraded its consensus mechanism from one relying on computational effort to capital at risk.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The network’s consensus mechanism was upgraded successfully on 15 September 2022, resulting in an instant decrease of 99.99% is network energy usage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://liamellul.github.io/images/customer-discovery/eth-staking/c2a4a4e411dc655e4eced900da39c2d6.png&#34; alt=&#34;img2&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://ccaf.io/cbnsi/ethereum/ethereum_merge&#34;&gt;Cambridge Blockchain Network Sustainability Index&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://liamellul.github.io/images/customer-discovery/eth-staking/9698764b2afae25f4f676a37b3fedd91.png&#34; alt=&#34;img&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://digiconomist.net/ethereum-energy-consumption&#34;&gt;Via Digiconomist&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;network-participation-change&#34;&gt;Network participation change&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Ethereum network upgrade reduced the network energy requirements, but also incorporated a system where more individual participants in the Ethereum network can participate in it&amp;rsquo;s consensus mechanism via a new action known as “Staking”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;-miners-are-out&#34;&gt;🚫 Miners are out&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the Proof of work phase of Ethereum,  participants called “miners” used powerful computers to solve difficult, arbitrary math puzzles to develop network consensus. By solving hard problems proves that resources were expended by the miner. These costs make it extremely difficult to justify attacking the network and breaking Bitcoin.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;-validators-are-in&#34;&gt;✅ Validators are in&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the current proof of stake phase of Ethereum the role of miner are replaced by the role of validator. Validators are responsible for verifying the transactions and adding new blocks to the blockchain. They are rewarded for their work with new ETH can can also be punished by losing ETH if they break any rules.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are 3 ways to participate in the new consensus mechanism and gain rewards in the Proof of Stake system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;solo-staking&#34;&gt;Solo-staking&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The most direct way to participate in the Ethereum consensus mechanism is to run your own validator node &amp;ndash; something known as &amp;ldquo;solo-staking&amp;rdquo;. There are some requirements involved here namely:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You need 32 ETH as a capital requirement (~$55,000 USD as of Oct 2023).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A dedicated computer/ server to run the validator software.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Must manage and ensure their node is running and online, or risk penalties.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A technical understanding of linux and command line tools for node set-up.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Staked ETH is locked and not accessible.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This option is the most &amp;ldquo;home grown&amp;rdquo; option and as a result you gain unmediated access to the full reward of validating blocks and transactions, but incurring operational costs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s very cool to see some hardware providers such as &lt;a href=&#34;https://dappnode.com/&#34;&gt;dappnode&lt;/a&gt; attempting to consumerize this experience with dedicated hardware for staking akin to an Apple TV!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;decentralized-staking-pools&#34;&gt;Decentralized Staking Pools&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is an option with more technical support and lower capital requirements that is worth mentioning and that is Staking Pools. This involves aggregating the stakes of multiple participants to reach the 32 ETH required for a validator. In this pooled model the rewards and penalties are shared among the participants.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The experience of staking pools is highly dependent on the service. The most novel provider in this space I&amp;rsquo;ve seen is &lt;a href=&#34;rocketpool.net&#34;&gt;Rocket Pool&lt;/a&gt;. They have designed a way to form staking pools in a decentralized manner.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rocketpool appeals to participants seeking:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;improved technical support&lt;/strong&gt;: they maintain their own node software and have a developer focused community.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;lower capital requirements&lt;/strong&gt;: the total cost to become a validator in a &amp;ldquo;mini-pool&amp;rdquo; is 10.4 ETH rather than 32 ETH. The big catch here is that 2.4 ETH worth of this needs to be purchased as &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.coingecko.com/en/coins/rocket-pool&#34;&gt;$RPL&lt;/a&gt; which introduces real price risk and mixes in the investment from one purely as ETH to also the $RPL token.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;differentiated commercial offer&lt;/strong&gt;: Rocketpool has an interesting commission model whereby the rate adjusts based on the ratio of node operators to stakers within the network.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Rocketpool risks&lt;/strong&gt;
The two ky risks for Rocketpool &amp;ldquo;mini-pool&amp;rdquo; participants is smart contract risk and also notably the price risk on $RPL collateral.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are other projects building decentralized staking pools such as &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/divastaking&#34;&gt;Diva staking&lt;/a&gt; but this project is still early in development and not yet in full production. From their initial designs it looks as though the risk exposure of the participant it entirely contained to ETH price action and smart contract risk.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;liquid-staking&#34;&gt;Liquid Staking&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Liquid Staking is the most accessible and popular kind of participation by ETH holders in the consensus mechanism of Ethereum. It allows a participant to stake their ETH while remaining while still having a liquid, transferable representation of their staked assets. This is achieved through receiving a Liquid Staking Token (LST) which is a receipt that can exchanged for the ETH deposit + staking fees or penalties incurred. While more accessible to smaller ETH holders to stake their ETH the LST token is also recognized by DeFi protocols who accept it as a collateral for loans.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are a number of providers of liquid staking the main ones being:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Liquid staking provider:&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;LST name&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://defillama.com/protocol/lido&#34;&gt;Lido&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;stETH&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://defillama.com/protocol/rocket-pool&#34;&gt;Rocketpool&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;rETH&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://defillama.com/protocol/binance-staked-eth&#34;&gt;Binance ETH Staking&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;wBETH&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://defillama.com/protocol/frax-ether&#34;&gt;Frax Ether&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;sfrxETH&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is currently controversy around which solution is &amp;ldquo;best&amp;rdquo; and this area is constantly evolving so I expect many changes and new innovations to occur around how ETH Stake is acquired and distributed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the time of writing Lido is by far the most popular solution comprising ~77% of all liquid staking and ~32% of all ETH Staked. This is due to stETH&amp;rsquo;s integration with other DeFi dApps such as decentralized exchanges and loan providers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;summing-up&#34;&gt;Summing up&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the first a dip in the water as I learn more about the inner workings of Ethereum. I wanted could have gone much deeper into specific solutions and their mechanics but I will keep this one pretty high level.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The TLDR is that Ethereum changed how it worked to allow participants to Stake ETH to validate transactions. This resulted in a wave of solutions to help participants Stake their ETH based on their preferences.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are only one year in post merge so I expect much more innovation to occur into the future!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Customer Development is Faith Making</title>
      <link>https://liamellul.github.io/posts/customer-discovery/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 Sep 2023 11:30:59 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://liamellul.github.io/posts/customer-discovery/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Customer discovery in early stage projects is that of a ​&lt;em&gt;faith maker&lt;/em&gt;​. By this I mean you are producing faith in customers that through commitment to your promises alone they can manifest the solution to their issue.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These faithful customer commitments are then traded to your developers to give them faith that they are creating a thing which has enduring value and use. With diligent expectation management and commitment qualification the faith produced in both the customer and the developers results in a self fulfilling prophecy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;to-do-this-you-need-to&#34;&gt;To do this you need to:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Aquire customer&amp;rsquo;s time.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Produce value from customer&amp;rsquo;s time.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Develop customer commitments.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;only-faith-can-solve-impossible-logic&#34;&gt;Only faith can solve impossible logic&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It goes by many names, “the cold start problem”, the the &amp;ldquo;chicken and the egg problem&amp;rdquo; or a &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Catch-22_(logic)&#34;&gt;catch-22&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An unsolvable issue that:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A requires B to be satisfied&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;B requires A to be satisfied&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this context:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You need to aquire committed customers (A) to validate and build something compelling (B).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You need to validate and build something  compelling (B) to acquire committed customers (A).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This paradox pervades the entire process when validating product market fit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What results is a confidence game based on a diligent qualification and balance of customer needs (is this valuable to them) business viability (is this valuable to me) and feasibility (is this something we can resource).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;acquiring-customer-time&#34;&gt;Acquiring customer time&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://liamellul.github.io/images/customer-discovery/customer-time1.png&#34; alt=&#34;img1&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First you need to find the customers you want to speak with and then schedule time to meet. This is in my experience the most grinding and monotonous work that requires the most discipline to do consistently.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some terminology:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Target&lt;/strong&gt; is a potential customer (Name, Company, Position, Contact) you will be reaching out to their time.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Customer&lt;/strong&gt; is a person with discretion and authority over budget allocations and who is negatively impacted by the problem you are solving.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Outreach&lt;/strong&gt; is the process of reaching out to the Target and following up if they don&amp;rsquo;t respond and providing further information if they do respond. This is typically through communications channels such as LinkedIn (yes that’s right!), Twitter, Email, Phone or Referral. Campaigns typically employ multiple channels.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Campaign&lt;/strong&gt; is the process of collecting a list of targets contact information and then reaching out to them.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Appointment&lt;/strong&gt; this is the time acquired to conduct a discovery call where you will be envisaging and producing faithful customer commitment.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sequencing&lt;/strong&gt; refers to an automated string of prompts to follow up with the contact.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This will almost always take trial and error and campaign retrospectives to fine tune who gives you time and who the right customer is. The most important thing is to constantly adjust the messaging to seek what is most resonant and engaging.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;a-note-on-tooling&#34;&gt;A note on tooling&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I use process automation tools, but this is secondary. I got some great advice once:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;If you ever run into an automation problem: Google &amp;ldquo;tool for fixing X problem&amp;rdquo; and there will be a dev team probably somewhere in Eastern Europe that has a B2B SaaS app that solves the problem.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ll include details on my own tooling but the key is the refinement of your outreach communication to be the most resonant. If you find something that lands you need to add this immediately. There is no tool that will be a magic bullet! The fundamentals are whether you are offering something people will trade their time for. Tooling simply helps scale this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;targeting&#34;&gt;Targeting&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is where you define who you want to contact and obtain their contact information. I tend to start this search for companies based on industry, location, and headcount as a first step. Once I have a list of companies I then filter for specific position names which can be used to get more contact information.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The following will get a list of Names, Job Titles, LinkedIn URLs, emails and phone numbers:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I use Crunchbase or Sales Navigator to filter for companies based on location, industry, size etc.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I then use Sales Navigator to filter for people at the companies (e.g. CXO). People typically have their first and last names and their most recent company updated so it is a good primary data source.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Once I have the query I use Evaboot to extract a CSV of all of the people&amp;rsquo;s names from LinkedIn within a search query, positions and LinkedIn profiles.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I also use this primary data to get phone numbers and business emails.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Roles and industries should be constantly being adjusted based on respondent types and their commitment.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;outreach--follow-ups&#34;&gt;Outreach &amp;amp; Follow-Ups&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I prefer a softer approach for reaching out to people I don&amp;rsquo;t have a relationship with by sending LinkedIn connection requests with all of targets and interacting with their content. If they accept my connection request, I then message them and follow up if they don&amp;rsquo;t reply. LinkedIn might be useless for you but lots of buyers in my context use and are engaged with LinkedIn.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On average I get about 50% connection rate and a 10% reply rate of which about 30% who reply (3% net) set appointments. This is mostly a byproduct of people not using LinkedIn. So after a couple of weeks it&amp;rsquo;s best to try a different approach for those who aren&amp;rsquo;t determined as non-active on LinkedIn.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Example&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Configure a campaign sequence in Dripify to connect, interact with LinkedIn content automatically. The most important part here is the opening message “hook” which compresses you more resonant stuff. This takes trial and error to get right.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Feed the CSV of Linkedin URL profiles into the Dripify and begin the campaign.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Scheduling links are generally accepted. If on the fence many will ask for an email with more info. Send this as a &lt;em&gt;sequence&lt;/em&gt; so you don&amp;rsquo;t have to put energy into manual follow-ups.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you get desperate there are many partnership forms on company websites. Just make sure it is partnership/procurement and not going through to a sales team for a product demo. This will be a waste of your time for both you and them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;producing-value-with-customer-time&#34;&gt;Producing value with customer time&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://liamellul.github.io/images/customer-discovery/value-from-time.png&#34; alt=&#34;img2&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The faith making process occurs when you use the customer’s time to envisage solutions which resonate with them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The properties of “resonant” are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;​&lt;strong&gt;Engaged&lt;/strong&gt;​: customer naturally moves to talk about a problem area or starts making requests, talks about dissatisfaction about something they’ve tried&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;​&lt;strong&gt;Low friction&lt;/strong&gt;​: customer agrees and affirms a solution suggestion relating to a problem that they have, conversation flows forward and suggestion is accepted and appreciated.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;​&lt;strong&gt;Emotionally connected&lt;/strong&gt;​: actively affirms and encourages the solution that has been presented.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The difference between &lt;em&gt;Solution&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Product&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Solution&lt;/strong&gt; is the abstract approach of addressing a problem.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Product&lt;/strong&gt; is the tangible offering that embodies the solution.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You want to be 51% presenting and selling what has been validated while still 49% discovering and validating new areas of the solution. I put these percentages in to illustrate that the bias is always to present and secure increasingly explicit commitment while still remaining open mind to new areas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The art is to know what is enough for the initial manifestation of a solution commonly described as the Minimum Viable Product. In the below diagram I illustrate the process of selling what you have defined in the solution space validating the common collection of resonant points.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://liamellul.github.io/images/customer-discovery/mvp-illustration.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;img3&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is a concept known as the &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pareto_principle&#34;&gt;Pareto principle&lt;/a&gt; which states that for many outcomes, roughly 80% of consequences come from 20% of causes. In the world of turning things that resonate into a solution this very much applies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Understanding the 20% that satisfies the 80% of issues de-risks you investing resources into things that are low impact or manifesting more things that are necessary!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;developing-customer-commitments&#34;&gt;Developing customer commitments&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The more time you spend producing value using customer&amp;rsquo;s time the more value you will produce by validating the solution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are two rules that help develop customer commitments:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Never leave a call without a follow up time in the calendar.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Always have a “go-do” action defined. Use the next calendar time as the deadline.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This creates a “force function” as customers are now trading their time to see it come to life. If these haven&amp;rsquo;t been explicitly defined and communicated the engagement will fade away. When you lose a customer&amp;rsquo;s time it&amp;rsquo;s hard to get it back.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Have somewhere where you can track the engagements. CRMs are fine for contact management but the sales stage features will be of little value. The key is to have a place where you can track the contacts who are engaged with next actions and notes. If someone wants to stop meeting series find out why. Things that end an engagement can be important data-points.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;in-closing&#34;&gt;In closing&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Customer discovery is a process of faith making &amp;ndash; between the customer and the development team to overcome the cold start paradox.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Faith making is performed by first acquiring customer time. Customer’s time is only valuable if you are able to envisage solutions that resonate and have the structure to develop the commitments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally diligence is required to prioritize and map the key components of the solution to de-risk wasting resources.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hope this has been helpful and I welcome feedback!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    
    
    <item>
      <title>I ♡ Joe Rogan: a meditation on parasocial relationships</title>
      <link>https://liamellul.github.io/posts/i-love-joe-rogan/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 16 Sep 2022 18:26:13 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://liamellul.github.io/posts/i-love-joe-rogan/</guid>
      <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Parasocial Interaction:&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;em&gt;An exposure that garners interest in a persona and becomes a parasocial relationship after repeated exposure to the media persona causes the media user to develop illusions of intimacy, friendship, and identification.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was 20 in 2012. I’d broken up with my first girlfriend and was basking in a delightful void.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I discovered Joe Rogan, and I’d listen to him talk with guests on his podcast.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It felt like I had friends over, sitting in my living room joining the sesh.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Joe was cool. A fighter. A comedian. His lifestyle. His whacky friends. It was beyond reality TV. I imagined being on his show, rehearsing in my head what I would say.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Joe’s persona was a powerful projection as I navigated my smoke-filled chasm of early audulthood.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://liamellul.github.io/images/joe-rogan/adbfd154-2adb-4aa7-b523-95db2f801785_768x512.webp&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;10 years later. 2022. I’m back in the void. In a new city. My social circle has shrunk, so to fill the gap I reconnect with my old friend: Joe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My YouTube feed is filled with clips of Joe and his comedian friends having a merry time talking and cracking jokes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I suspend my disbelief as I potter around the house, and in moments they feel like my friends too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then it hits me:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;i-am-observing-media-for-companionship&#34;&gt;I am observing media for companionship.&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;i-have-begun-to-substitute-social-interaction-with-parasocial-interaction&#34;&gt;I have begun to substitute social interaction with parasocial interaction.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://liamellul.github.io/images/joe-rogan/b7eefcf1-2812-4240-8cf8-a789deb41a2e_800x500.webp&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thinking back to 20-year-old Liam and the present 30-year-old Liam; there is a pattern. A pattern that hooks me into an overconsumption of content:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The experience of socializing with someone who has a thing I desire.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I can’t unsee this now. It’s everywhere&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I want to go deeper… throughout history… to see the persistence of this pattern through space and time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;parasocial-tv-media&#34;&gt;Parasocial TV Media&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;F.R.I.E.N.D.S exemplifies how parasocial relationships were developed using television.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://liamellul.github.io/images/joe-rogan/05b91966-bda7-4b2a-8e5c-11b29747693a_918x506.webp&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;
&lt;em&gt;&lt;div align=&#34;center&#34;&gt; Chandler and Co are here to distract you from the void. &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;90’s sitcoms transpired in apartments, where the audience would sit and watch TV after work, a ritual that fueled enduring parasocial interactions with the show.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The audience returns home deflated and socially isolated from living in a soul-crushing metropolis. F.R.I.E.N.D.S gives them social experiences with a communal, upbeat group of attractive (and incestuous) friends.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;F.R.I.E.N.D.S is a perfect projection of the audience’s desires.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://liamellul.github.io/images/joe-rogan/844d8514-64e3-46ab-b942-51bd67bae915_1454x1258.webp&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;
&lt;em&gt;&lt;div align=&#34;center&#34;&gt; ♫ I&amp;rsquo;ll be there for you ♫  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The opening song “I’ll Be There For You” acknowledges the audience’s suffering and that the show will be there for [them], to relieve their existential dread:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;♫&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So no one told you life was gonna be this way&lt;br&gt;
Your job&amp;rsquo;s a joke, you&amp;rsquo;re broke, your love life&amp;rsquo;s D.O.A. (Dead On Arrival)&lt;br&gt;
It&amp;rsquo;s like you&amp;rsquo;re always stuck in second gear&lt;br&gt;
When it hasn&amp;rsquo;t been your day, your week, your month, or even your year, but&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ll be there for you&lt;br&gt;
When the rain starts to pour 😭&lt;br&gt;
I&amp;rsquo;ll be there for you&lt;br&gt;
(Like I&amp;rsquo;ve been there before)&lt;br&gt;
I&amp;rsquo;ll be there for you&lt;br&gt;
(&amp;lsquo;Cause you&amp;rsquo;re there for me too)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;♫&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The simulation of socializing with people who have something we desire.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Repeated interactions with the media are reinforced by ritual.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;parasocial-print-media&#34;&gt;Parasocial print media&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before TV, muscular heroes would appear episodically on the newsstands and dominate mass media. They were more accessible and engaging than books and exploded in popularity during the 1940s and 1950s.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The heroes presented a persona in possession of things the audience, typically young boys desire: muscular strength, courage, and power.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://liamellul.github.io/images/joe-rogan/abd71c4c-9aaa-4228-bd5b-92406ec1e7ca_600x531.webp&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;
&lt;em&gt;&lt;div align = &#34;center&#34; &gt;Squint your eyes and it’s a podcast about MMA.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Readers quickly bonded to their favorite hero and habitually returned to buy the latest issue to resolve the cliffhanger from the previous episode.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://liamellul.github.io/images/joe-rogan/83861f8f-f7ce-460b-a96b-756341a3ff76_1400x1028.webp&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The heroes’ world-saving optimism was a source of hope amidst a society recovering from the great depression.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;parasocial-interactions-before-mass-media&#34;&gt;Parasocial interactions before mass media&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://liamellul.github.io/images/joe-rogan/e4dde96d-8838-4e1a-97ba-aceca6941d54_817x427.webp&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before mass media, parasocial relationships were fostered through ceremonies, routine, and religious worship. The media personas of this era were gods, heroes, prophets, philosophers, and kings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The masses were told stories of these personas from speakers in close physical proximity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://liamellul.github.io/images/joe-rogan/1aee0301-69ce-43da-8ce6-84d596fb4cd9_800x898.webp&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;div align = &#34;center&#34; &gt;Jesus blowing up his follower count during the Sermon on the Mount.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The greeks had gods such as Zeus, Athena, and heroes like Hercules. A rich menagerie of personas appealed to and created bonds with the audiences and became interwoven into the social order.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Eastern cultures produced devotion to personas such as the Hindu deities which due to their religious-based interactions, hold cultural relevance to this day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://liamellul.github.io/images/joe-rogan/120cdb4f-37c0-4210-b011-23ee2d7086d4_550x633.webp&#34; alt=&#34;img&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;reconciling-my-feelings-for-joe-rogan&#34;&gt;Reconciling my feelings for Joe Rogan&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We return to 2022, where I sit and watch clips of Joe and his comedian friends.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Are parasocial relationships good or bad?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At one end of the spectrum, it is entertainment, a way to relax. On the other end, the consumption of personas strengthen a coping strategy that restrains positive action to improve your situation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my case the answer (projection) is clear:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I need to get off my iPad, leave my apartment and socialize with people at the local comedy club.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    
    
    
  </channel>
</rss>
