<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Tags on Liam Ellul&#39;s Blog</title>
    <link>https://liamellul.github.io/tags/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Tags on Liam Ellul&#39;s Blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    
	<atom:link href="https://liamellul.github.io/tags/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Customer Development is Faith Making</title>
      <link>https://liamellul.github.io/posts/customer-discovery/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 Sep 2023 11:30:59 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://liamellul.github.io/posts/customer-discovery/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Customer discovery in early stage projects is that of a ​&lt;em&gt;faith maker&lt;/em&gt;​. By this I mean you are producing faith in customers that through commitment to your promises alone they can manifest the solution to their issue.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These faithful customer commitments are then traded to your developers to give them faith that they are creating a thing which has enduring value and use. With diligent expectation management and commitment qualification the faith produced in both the customer and the developers results in a self fulfilling prophecy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;to-do-this-you-need-to&#34;&gt;To do this you need to:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Aquire customer&amp;rsquo;s time.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Produce value from customer&amp;rsquo;s time.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Develop customer commitments.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;only-faith-can-solve-impossible-logic&#34;&gt;Only faith can solve impossible logic&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It goes by many names, “the cold start problem”, the the &amp;ldquo;chicken and the egg problem&amp;rdquo; or a &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Catch-22_(logic)&#34;&gt;catch-22&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An unsolvable issue that:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A requires B to be satisfied&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;B requires A to be satisfied&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this context:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You need to aquire committed customers (A) to validate and build something compelling (B).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You need to validate and build something  compelling (B) to acquire committed customers (A).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This paradox pervades the entire process when validating product market fit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What results is a confidence game based on a diligent qualification and balance of customer needs (is this valuable to them) business viability (is this valuable to me) and feasibility (is this something we can resource).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;acquiring-customer-time&#34;&gt;Acquiring customer time&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://liamellul.github.io/images/customer-discovery/customer-time1.png&#34; alt=&#34;img1&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First you need to find the customers you want to speak with and then schedule time to meet. This is in my experience the most grinding and monotonous work that requires the most discipline to do consistently.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some terminology:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Target&lt;/strong&gt; is a potential customer (Name, Company, Position, Contact) you will be reaching out to their time.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Customer&lt;/strong&gt; is a person with discretion and authority over budget allocations and who is negatively impacted by the problem you are solving.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Outreach&lt;/strong&gt; is the process of reaching out to the Target and following up if they don&amp;rsquo;t respond and providing further information if they do respond. This is typically through communications channels such as LinkedIn (yes that’s right!), Twitter, Email, Phone or Referral. Campaigns typically employ multiple channels.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Campaign&lt;/strong&gt; is the process of collecting a list of targets contact information and then reaching out to them.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Appointment&lt;/strong&gt; this is the time acquired to conduct a discovery call where you will be envisaging and producing faithful customer commitment.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sequencing&lt;/strong&gt; refers to an automated string of prompts to follow up with the contact.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This will almost always take trial and error and campaign retrospectives to fine tune who gives you time and who the right customer is. The most important thing is to constantly adjust the messaging to seek what is most resonant and engaging.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;a-note-on-tooling&#34;&gt;A note on tooling&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I use process automation tools, but this is secondary. I got some great advice once:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;If you ever run into an automation problem: Google &amp;ldquo;tool for fixing X problem&amp;rdquo; and there will be a dev team probably somewhere in Eastern Europe that has a B2B SaaS app that solves the problem.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ll include details on my own tooling but the key is the refinement of your outreach communication to be the most resonant. If you find something that lands you need to add this immediately. There is no tool that will be a magic bullet! The fundamentals are whether you are offering something people will trade their time for. Tooling simply helps scale this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;targeting&#34;&gt;Targeting&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is where you define who you want to contact and obtain their contact information. I tend to start this search for companies based on industry, location, and headcount as a first step. Once I have a list of companies I then filter for specific position names which can be used to get more contact information.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The following will get a list of Names, Job Titles, LinkedIn URLs, emails and phone numbers:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I use Crunchbase or Sales Navigator to filter for companies based on location, industry, size etc.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I then use Sales Navigator to filter for people at the companies (e.g. CXO). People typically have their first and last names and their most recent company updated so it is a good primary data source.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Once I have the query I use Evaboot to extract a CSV of all of the people&amp;rsquo;s names from LinkedIn within a search query, positions and LinkedIn profiles.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I also use this primary data to get phone numbers and business emails.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Roles and industries should be constantly being adjusted based on respondent types and their commitment.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;outreach--follow-ups&#34;&gt;Outreach &amp;amp; Follow-Ups&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I prefer a softer approach for reaching out to people I don&amp;rsquo;t have a relationship with by sending LinkedIn connection requests with all of targets and interacting with their content. If they accept my connection request, I then message them and follow up if they don&amp;rsquo;t reply. LinkedIn might be useless for you but lots of buyers in my context use and are engaged with LinkedIn.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On average I get about 50% connection rate and a 10% reply rate of which about 30% who reply (3% net) set appointments. This is mostly a byproduct of people not using LinkedIn. So after a couple of weeks it&amp;rsquo;s best to try a different approach for those who aren&amp;rsquo;t determined as non-active on LinkedIn.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Example&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Configure a campaign sequence in Dripify to connect, interact with LinkedIn content automatically. The most important part here is the opening message “hook” which compresses you more resonant stuff. This takes trial and error to get right.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Feed the CSV of Linkedin URL profiles into the Dripify and begin the campaign.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Scheduling links are generally accepted. If on the fence many will ask for an email with more info. Send this as a &lt;em&gt;sequence&lt;/em&gt; so you don&amp;rsquo;t have to put energy into manual follow-ups.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you get desperate there are many partnership forms on company websites. Just make sure it is partnership/procurement and not going through to a sales team for a product demo. This will be a waste of your time for both you and them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;producing-value-with-customer-time&#34;&gt;Producing value with customer time&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://liamellul.github.io/images/customer-discovery/value-from-time.png&#34; alt=&#34;img2&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The faith making process occurs when you use the customer’s time to envisage solutions which resonate with them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The properties of “resonant” are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;​&lt;strong&gt;Engaged&lt;/strong&gt;​: customer naturally moves to talk about a problem area or starts making requests, talks about dissatisfaction about something they’ve tried&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;​&lt;strong&gt;Low friction&lt;/strong&gt;​: customer agrees and affirms a solution suggestion relating to a problem that they have, conversation flows forward and suggestion is accepted and appreciated.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;​&lt;strong&gt;Emotionally connected&lt;/strong&gt;​: actively affirms and encourages the solution that has been presented.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The difference between &lt;em&gt;Solution&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Product&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Solution&lt;/strong&gt; is the abstract approach of addressing a problem.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Product&lt;/strong&gt; is the tangible offering that embodies the solution.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You want to be 51% presenting and selling what has been validated while still 49% discovering and validating new areas of the solution. I put these percentages in to illustrate that the bias is always to present and secure increasingly explicit commitment while still remaining open mind to new areas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The art is to know what is enough for the initial manifestation of a solution commonly described as the Minimum Viable Product. In the below diagram I illustrate the process of selling what you have defined in the solution space validating the common collection of resonant points.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://liamellul.github.io/images/customer-discovery/mvp-illustration.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;img3&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is a concept known as the &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pareto_principle&#34;&gt;Pareto principle&lt;/a&gt; which states that for many outcomes, roughly 80% of consequences come from 20% of causes. In the world of turning things that resonate into a solution this very much applies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Understanding the 20% that satisfies the 80% of issues de-risks you investing resources into things that are low impact or manifesting more things that are necessary!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;developing-customer-commitments&#34;&gt;Developing customer commitments&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The more time you spend producing value using customer&amp;rsquo;s time the more value you will produce by validating the solution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are two rules that help develop customer commitments:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Never leave a call without a follow up time in the calendar.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Always have a “go-do” action defined. Use the next calendar time as the deadline.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This creates a “force function” as customers are now trading their time to see it come to life. If these haven&amp;rsquo;t been explicitly defined and communicated the engagement will fade away. When you lose a customer&amp;rsquo;s time it&amp;rsquo;s hard to get it back.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Have somewhere where you can track the engagements. CRMs are fine for contact management but the sales stage features will be of little value. The key is to have a place where you can track the contacts who are engaged with next actions and notes. If someone wants to stop meeting series find out why. Things that end an engagement can be important data-points.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;in-closing&#34;&gt;In closing&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Customer discovery is a process of faith making &amp;ndash; between the customer and the development team to overcome the cold start paradox.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Faith making is performed by first acquiring customer time. Customer’s time is only valuable if you are able to envisage solutions that resonate and have the structure to develop the commitments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally diligence is required to prioritis\ze and map the key components of the solution to de-risk wasting resources.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hope this has been helpful and I welcome feedback!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    
    
    
  </channel>
</rss>
